I've been looking at um majima
140 it's um I forget the exact name of
it but it's basically it goes through
the six elements
and um it's a it's a discussion
about this is the suo where the Buddha
is going and he asks if he can stay in
somebody's Woodshed and he says yes
there's somebody that's staying there
currently though um so he goes in and
the Buddha is he says oh wow this his
conduct is very inspiring he talks to
him he doesn't realize it's the
Buddha and so then he says all right let
me teach you the
and there are a number
of things that he he goes into namely
the the six
elements and then he talks about
equinity um well first it's with after
the after the Consciousness element he
goes into equinity and um kind
of goes through that stuff and um B
Pasco and I were discussing the
elements the other today I'm curious if
there's
a what what would be a more practical
way of
approaching that in your
experience well it would be basically
you have to start with what you
have um in other words you know like six
elements well you're not going to be
contemplating the fifth or the sixth
unless you have discerned the first one
so for somebody the starting point the
first element is all six elements you
know the first jna is all four
janas you won't be even correctly being
able to think about the second or the
third let alone fourth if you have not
established yourself in the first it's
inconceivable even theoretically you
will not be able to grasp it and same
goes for any um aspect of contemplation
so so in case in terms of six elements
or casinos and so on um the first one is
the direction of all the elements that
you can
develop so what is the first most
obvious element that you have pair with
Earth no more obvious than that let's
see Earth Earth okay so for me that's an
idea for you maybe it's more practical
but generally what's something that you
cannot avoid whether you take it as an
idea or not you are pair with it
so the body the body it's your basically
it's the direction of the elements of
all of
them so that's how you start to
practically contemplate it well in order
to start to practically contemplated
first you need to contain the
body because for as long as a person is
acting out of Greater version of
delusion um the body that exists for them so to
um the body that exists for them so to
speak the body that they would see when
they look at what the body is is the
body on the level of sense objects
because that's where they're already
dependent on and that's already not the body um
on and that's already not the body um
seen accurately enough that's not that
immediate body you're paid with that's
kind of the body that's now the result
of your sensual proliferation and
non-restraint so if a person contains
them rightly then that which is left
there within that containment
approximates the body more accurately
that which the body is in your
experience but
fundamentally um in order to then on top of that write
um in order to then on top of that write
containment in order to
discern that which body is in your
experience rightly you have to learn how to attend
rightly you have to learn how to attend
to it
indirectly as you spoke before any
direct attempted attend attending to
your body it's going to be attending to
the sense objects so it's not going to
be the body on the level of sense
organs and uh so then it's yeah learning
how to see it
peripherally in other words whatever
you're currently attending without
shifting your attention too much you
want to
discern that this
body has to be implied in whatever your
mind is currently preoccupied with has
to be there as an underlying basis and
if you keep Discerning that sufficient
amount of
times um it will then uh reveal itself
so to speak that which you are
Discerning as implicit is factually
implicit that body is factually there as
a basis of this opinion it's just that
you again you overlook
it um you over attend it or you
completely ignore it but
attending to it indirectly in other
words you attend to something else so to
speak whatever takes your attention it
doesn't matter what you attend basically
what matters is to recognize that
whatever you're attending the source of
this experience as a whole of attending
to this flowboards now is the existing
body as the six sent space here and now
that is the that image becomes the
implicit base for everything that I'm
engaged with and because things are
factually so
uh then that image will settle in so to
speak then you wouldn't have to keep
evoking it rightly it would be seen as
but no it can't be otherwise like even
if I forget about the body and don't
have these images of the body being
implicit in this experience as a whole
it is
so and that understanding has kind of
sunk deeper and sunk through so to speak
it's it sort of
s um and that's already the
contemplation of the element the element
of Earth obviously in this case then you
can take it further but even if you
don't take it further this in and of
itself is enough mindfulness of the body
or not forgetfulness of the implicit
body to the extent necessary it's enough
for the final knowledge as the Sati
patan says and that's exactly it see how how
says and that's exactly it see how how
do
you not forget about
something do you constantly keep it in
front of your eyes no you keep it at the
back of your mind and that's exactly why
Sati patana of the body is or any for
that matter practice of Sati
memory so you're not recollecting the
body through directly observing it
you're recollecting it as an
image of Your World dependent upon the
body so that's already a form of
knowledge like write
memory as we said that
before so just just have a memory of
your body being there regardless of what
you're currently engaging with past
present future doesn't matter don't
completely forget that your body has to
be
there and practice it on that level see
that's not really that hard thing to do
what's hard is to contain yourself to
stay on that level because the tendency
of craving views of course and
everything else will want to make you
overly Define it yeah but if I attend to
it even harder
feel it for what it is that's how I'll
get to that body and the more you do it
the further away from the actual body
you go because in that case you're actually
go because in that case you're actually
overlooking it yeah in doing that it's
you're overtightening you're over um tightening
overtightening you're over um tightening
your focus ring basically so it's it's
it's going to focus on something past
the body it will it will
shift and if somebody is recollecting
the body in this sense
correctly then why is that right
progress how is that come to uproot
feathers why is that so anybody
so anybody
else because it is exactly through
engaging through well engaging in a whome conduct
through well engaging in a whome conduct
or fueling the factors that you overlook
the
body but no what he's asking is so
you're not engaging in the conduct and
you're recollecting it rightly why is
that resulting in uprooting of the fets
why would that
result in in in clearing away of
impurities well because they're mutually
exclusive but why I well like I said
because whenever you're acting out of
the feathers you are necessarily
overlooking the body and if you are not
overlooking the body implies that you
are not acting in those ways you can't
see the body right circularity now no
the point is yes if you don't act out
and if you're rightly mindful you're
appro in the fetus question why why is
it apprting the fetus what is it that
when you are correctly recollecting the
body
that environment is unsuitable for the
Persistence of the fets for the growth
of the
fets it's actually killing them off
they're fading away for as long as that
right environment is maintained
internally why is that what is the kind
of acute aspect of that the right order
is basically established and maintain
yeah and so what does the right order
mean what is what is impossible to do or
even conceive when the right orders is
established ownership exactly so it's
impossible that body that you see
indirectly as an implicit phenomenon
that endures regardless of present past
future engagement doesn't matter doesn't
matter the extent the intensity of your
engagements that body there if it's seen
it cannot be owned it's unable it's seen
as a thing that's that's that's not in
your control thoroughly and that's why
if you sustain it sufficiently enough it
would like like seep into all the other
more acute engaged activated aspects of
your experience that they would then
become equally unable you'll be
dispassionate towards
them now obviously that what that extent
is well that can only be measured in
hindsight that's why you can't have too
much of
mindfulness you can't have too much of
the right recollection if you dedicate
your whole time every single day or just
recall every single moment of your
waking time to not forgetting the
endurance of the body here and now it
cannot result in too much it cannot
result obviously if you try to over
attend to it and overly clarify it well
that can be too much but that means
you're already not recollecting it
rightly because that's another question
what is what is memory how do you
remember things you mean anything colloquially
things you mean anything colloquially
just in the broadest sense like what is
like obviously you know putting aside
the the the like what's your name and
stuff well no putting aside the kind of
the whole like misguided scientific
views of how memories imprint in your
brain and
what uh that's not how it appears for
you from your point of view so from your
point of view what is a
memory how do you recollect things it's
an image it's an image yeah but how do
you do that how do you recollect things
by
unending by by sure by attending like
exactly by by being by becoming by un
absorbing from whatever you might have
been uh absorbed in so you have to kind
of step back like that's already what's
known as an active reflection step back
on your situation even if you don't
necessarily think in terms of your
situation so it's like oh remember
something and you could even kind of oh
remember something from yesterday give
me an event from yesterday oh can you
remember something from approximately 10
years ago and you count the numbers and
remember oh yeah that was like 10 years
ago so you could selectively even
remember various other
things it's also relational like like
memory not being isolated images but
it's sort of like a web like different
memories so the so the more related the
easier it is to recollect yeah they they
remind you of other things and so on but
are you really doing the remembering
is that something that you
do you is also as in like do you like
like just go and find that memory or you
are a sorry you are you in a Comm no no no
a sorry you are you in a Comm no no no
I'm in colloquially I'm not I'm not like
trying to catch on a jargon now you but
there is no you and stuff like that no
no I mean just you do you do you
remember it how do you remember
it well it's presented it's
presented so presented to what
to
attention as a possibility that's what
you're saying it's basically your mind
is that which has memories that that
mind you're paid
with they exist for it they are in its
own domain they're not in your domain so
to speak so everything is already
implicit to a degree like whatever now
it has sort of the significance of being
here it's it's shaped by the whole fresh
memory of coming here decide to come
here for one reason or the other so it's
not like that you're always they
entirely encapsuled in the present
moment without any kind of connection
with these things that were before or
things that are implicit as they're
going to be
after so that's the whole like past is
already in your present implicit and so
is the future so past is present future
is present and present is present that's
already how things exist and from that
point of view you realize
images that you have now immediately are
already on the level of that faculty of
memory the current images you realize
there is no difference the only
difference is it like oh is it like here
now or like 10 minutes ago but from your
point of view where your mind is there
are images that present itself that's
why again if that mind gets expanded as
the suit has described gets fully
abandoned sensuality purifies itself
from All Things becomes very pliable
well you would remember far more than
than 10 years or 10 lifetimes you could
remember a lot more because again it was
the mind and images existing in the same
sense that I exist with the eye
objects so the only reason a person
might feel like I need to figure out the
workings of it is if they puts in that
relationship as I am doing this and this
is relevant for me but you don't need to
figure out the relationship how does the
eye see how does the nose smell how does
the Mind think it's irrelevant
all you need to do is develop this
passion towards
it and that's how you would understand
how it
works but by wanting to figure it out on
that specific overly attending level you
are appropriating it you're making it
yours when it isn't and that's already a
form of constricting your mind and that
constricted mind is not as is more
forgetful basically constricted mind
will find harder to recollect things
rightly or to broaden the context so if
you're focusing on your breath you're
forgetting the
body yeah yeah well it's even worse
because you you would probably be
focusing on your breath for some reason
or the other for some implication and
that's already a lack of context due to
the wrong
view yeah sure or Sensations and so but
the point is Sati means
memory so write
memory right memory of the body enduring
here is a necessary basis for for your
experience as a whole right memory of
the properties of the body enduring here
is a necessary basis for your experience
as a
whole the properties of the body being
four elements no properties of well yeah
four elements but properties of the four
elements meaning the the universal
characteristics you did not create it
you have no say in its existence it's
unable it's headed to to to to to sort
of
decomposition uh all of those things are
perpetually implicit in that body being
there and say an memory of your
breathing memory of your acute presently
enduring action of
breathing so you're not accessing it
through directly feeling you breathing and
directly feeling you breathing and
watching it you're accessing it through
the image of your mind recollecting it
indirect as a situation that you realize
you could bring yourself through
recollecting rightly through the past so
to speak through the memories you could
bring yourself to the present moment
here and
now but see it through the memory of the
present moment Here and Now not through
you attending the present moment here
and now that's the difference that's the
indirect way that's basically the oniso
that's how you rightly attend to
it you could say that this is the most
significant memory that act of breathing like in
memory that act of breathing like in
terms of your your existence oh yeah
that can have that those implications
would then reveal themselves more and
more but even if you like if you don't
go like for the furest steps of
anapanasati you know breathing like this
and regard your body in this way regard
your mind in that way just knowingly he
breaths out knowingly he breaths in yeah
cuz again memory knowledge memory is
something that you know things that you
know know do you need to constantly
observe them no once you know them once
you understood them they
disappear and then they just the mind
just recollects
them cuz mind and images that is that is
its domain that is its feeding ground
that's how it
exists so rather than trying to figure
out the relationship between the two
which results in as I said appropriation
of either or
both uh
develop this passion towards the entire
domain by by by favoring certain images
and memories rather than others so favor
those that are not they rooted in non-
greed non aversion that lead to this
passion that lead to disenchantment so
favor the the uh images of asuba favor
the asuba aspects of the images that you
recollect favor the the the Dua aspect
of of the images that you that you
recollect like establish them
peripherally as that
basis and see by the way like now
remember something from like 20 years
ago some event doesn't
matter obviously you unabsorbed yourself
from here to remember an image from 20 years
here to remember an image from 20 years
ago but that image from 20 years ago is
here yeah yeah so don't forget it to
come back here but while you remember it
through it see it being here as it is
the stove and the floor and all of us it
is here
factually Here and Now for you from your
point of view that memory doesn't matter
how old how far away it was it exists
here and now in the same sense these
other phenomena
exist because if it doesn't what did you
remember what are you talking about how
did you even understand my question my
suggest you wouldn't you wouldn't have
the subba is just the aspect that you
can take upon anything the aspect of the
ugly which is unavoidable by the fact
that well that the body is disgusting
yeah if the body were not disgusting
theba would not be possible but the body
is factually disgusting artifices oozing
sweat hair I mean isolate those things
outside of the intoxicated context to
beautiful and they're quite disgusting
as the Su say own mother would be
disgusted with her son with her child
body if she was to attend to it like
that it's a disgusting
thing he has been buried under under a
kind of wrongly directly attending to
only the pleasing aspects so you develop
this image now that proliferated and all
this kind of ugly not even associated
with it while it's still made out of
it because you couldn't be having any
perception of beautiful without the body
exactly and the body is factually
ugly so you just have to uncover that
but you won't uncover the ugliness if
you directly try to see
it but you will uncover it see when I
say like like the early all that is when
I say like oh you you find things there
already given or you find the body there
already given well that means it you you
remember it like you find this body already given
it like you find this body already given
existing this situation how do you find
it oh by remembering it as already being
there so finding things already existing
in the dependent of you it's already a
form of
memory just obvious you have more
immediate memories and then you have
more Distant Memories but either way
memory is really such it exists here and
again if you see that memory of the past
event or the present event here and now
as something that's here and now that is
the most acute well that's when
mindfulness becomes s when becomes
awareness but the point is to arrive
through that acute awareness Here and
Now not to directly leaping into it with
your attention as people would just
think they should do it but by
fortifying that indirect way of seeing
something that is here and now without
directly looking at
it and you start that by seeing the body
as a necessary basis to already endures
there and not forgetting
it always having the threat of
recollection connect to
it so that's why
obviously as I said container sensory
straint containing yourself containing
body actions are
completely not negotiable they have to
be developed beforehand but then
mentally as well you have to start
containing your mind from like just just
flowing into these abstractions or
fantasies or Delights and so on and just
confine it to where it is oh yeah even
if I allow this
choice of fantasizing about this or that
it will be done so Here and Now on the
base of this body
so let me not forget about the
body and if you don't forget about the
body entirely to that extent you'll be
anchored rightly so even thoughts that
presents will not take you too far out
where you
like kind of lost the thread lost the
connection and that's the anchor of
memory of the body body
memory and if you kind of start over
thinking what is the
memory or somebody who listening to this
might do that
well remember
anything just remember anything from the
past and then okay let me now in the
same manner remember this body here
that's all so let me not directly attend
to the body let me just remember
remember it that now while I'm thinking
this oh the body is here as a necessary
basis and have that image endure protect
it don't distract yourself for it from
it but obviously things will be coming
and going intensifying and fading away
regardless of what's coming coming or
going away you try and sustain the
necessity of the body being there for either
either
and then obviously you can apply the
same feelings in the other other side of
Tas same the mental s batana can you
have anything absolutely anything
discernable anything that you can
perceive that does not imply an image
mental image
inconceivable if you say I see nothing
it's just emptiness well that's an image
to that extent and that's why if you
were to practice memory of the body
rightly you would be practicing the
memory of the mental images
rightly memory of the Damas
correctly cuz yeah what are the thoughts
are they in your head in your
skull but it's kind of implicit like see
oh it's not there so it's kind of but is
it what what what's the measure for the
insideness of your thoughts no it's just
an assumption and to the to the to the
extent that you assume that your
thoughts are in your head
to that extent they're not here and
now they're over there and now true and
the reason why this is important like
why are you calling memory well because
it clearly shows the different direction
from which you have to approach that
indirect way as I keep saying you to see
your body indirectly CU even when people
hear that they would still try to attend
to it directly just think there is some
secret back door as opposed to okay I
don't look here but where do I look I
still try to like find it no it's on the
level of memory of anything
else so if you learn that that's where
you have to stop well you're closer to
doing it rightly you it's less likely
you'll be perpetually overdoing it or
overly attending it so remember
something from this
morning okay now in the same manner
remember something from right now that
that sort of pertains to your body
remember your body right
now and have that okay I remember that
okay leave it there and try to now
protect that image without what do I
next let me attend to I feel my knees
and Sensations and so on completely
unnecessary and actually it's it's
detrimental it takes you away from the
right
level and that's that body
there the image of that the right memory
of the body is as says it's body among
the bodies that you can experience it
stands for that that which body
is so it's efficient for
development memory of breathing has the
memory of the implicit
body and that's enough for fulfilling
the
satanus because the point of the right
recollection it's not as I said to
Define what that body truly is or to
press it is just to learn how to see it
to the right extent not too much not too
little and that's the hardest part
basically regarding practice not to
forget well to find the balance between
and not overend it will depend on people
like different people different
preferences different views some people
will be taken in overdoing it some
people will be taking direction of
underdo like ignoring it and so on so
but like
learning the extent that you should try
and like recognize and cultivate and
recognizing that it's not about directly
attending it or overly defining it but
it's certainly not about just just just
letting it float away and ignoring the
whole thing like no you got to recollect
but you got to leave it on the level of
that image of memory memory image
whichever you want to call it and then
eventually you get used to that you see
oh that memory that image is present
here and now while I'm talking about the
body and the image of it and that memory
endures in the same sense my sights
endure and that's already a form of
establishing mindfulness and then doesn't matter
mindfulness and then doesn't matter
what's happening on the level of other
senses that remains
unaffected but you have to kind of stick
with that well B through that um
satisfaction of wanting to exactly it's
basically your own C you set it up
rightly and then you're like well and
then there is this pressure to Next Step
yeah but by but by then not doing that
next step this is actually how you
undercut the desire and the grasping
Yeah by just letting it be there because
you cannot do this to the background
basically well yeah when it's set up
rightly it's threatening your you and
you wanting to it feels uncomfortable I
think for most people it would it would
certainly initially feel uncomfortable
it would feel incomplete yeah and if you
don't recognize see if you still judge
whether things are right or not whether
they go in the right direction or Not by
whether they feel complete or
incomplete you're judging with your own
misguided criteria but if you learn enough that
criteria but if you learn enough that
regardless of how incom complete in my
feel keep it
there if you keep it there sufficiently
enough you will recognize that it's it's
more than
complete it's like what I was saying
before that other s like imagine you you
know you know you're waiting for a bus
but there is no clear Mark where the bus
stop is so you stand at the spot cuz you
learn that you should stand there but
then but maybe I should go a bit forward
or maybe I should go a bit back or maybe
you know and because of it you keep
moving and and actually all the place
was right the fact is that you could not
contain yourself from overdoing
underdoing walking away what you missed
it you're not seeing
it so there is that degree of Faith
necessary to like but again not like
some magic will happen but more like
degree of Faith necessary to to
basically um give you the strength to
restrain yourself from overly defining
it or just completely ignoring it and
saying it doesn't matter what I think
everything will fall into place and
whatnot um so the point is to to
basically contain yourself within that
memory like so you have the right memory
and now you have the pressure the
tendency to clarify it more and to
attend to it even more specifically it's
like no I refrain that because if I do
that I'm losing the quality of this
memory the clarity of it so what if I
just protect it oh then I just drifting
away okay so let me bring it back now
cuz the mind is getting a bit too
loose so then you bring it back then you
pick it up sure pick up the memory but
now if you want to go go tighter with it
well then you don't do that so it's
learning how to stay on the right level
and for that you need exactly you need
to learn what the right level would be
and then just keep doing
it but the fact that you start from a
position of craving means
that I mean it's inevitable that it has
to be uncomfortable to start with to see
to see it yeah and that's what mean like
it would feel like in complete
insufficient from all the views that you
have and like craving to like complete
it fulfill it get get that Nana get that
freedom get that right View and that's
why not getting
it because you're acting out of your
own preconceived notion affected by
craving and assumption as to what is the
measure of um right or wrong what is the measure
of um right or wrong what is the measure
of beneficial and unbeneficial
yeah so you have to be willing to put
aside whatever you well include it yeah
you don't even have to you don't even
have to deal with it just include it so
you have say like I say like okay
recollect your body Here and Now
whatever position you're in okay you
know what you're position in see that's
already a right memory of the currently
enduring um body that's that's sort of a
necessary base for this
situation and now I have a tendency to
like grip it further there's this
pressure they want to make you attemp to
it even more specifically oh that is a
thing now that's within the experience of body
now that's within the experience of body
being here seated so instead of doing it
and forgetting about that body being
here as a seated sort of basis for your
experience you just include that
experience is another movement within
the body there that's seated that's
remained unmoved in that sense unchanged in that
unmoved in that sense unchanged in that
broader context you haven't stood
up so it's have changed oh so for as
long as I don't stand up I have a I have
a reference point
exactly so even if you lapse you
remember it and it's unchanged and it's
been enduring so you Al I don't even
have to constantly remember
it I just need to not when the choice to
stand up or do something present itself
I just need to see that ah there is a
choice if I don't act out of it
container remains unchanged even if I
don't think about it
it seems to me that even that um that
moment of like oh I forgot that I was
sitting you know I spent 30 minutes
thinking even having that
thought sort of implies that you already
know and you're and see even if even if
you forgot exactly so you forgot and
spent half an hour thinking about it and
it's like oh but the body is still
seated not nothing has changed thus my
mindfulness has remained
uninterrupted what would interrupt that
mindfulness even if you remain seated is
if the thoughts thoughts you had for
half an hour with thoughts fueled with
lust aversion that would interrupt
you but that was a choice you made there
was a choice you then kept perpetuating
so if that's your kind of as I said
before that's like the point you keep
your eye on not like what thought are
here every second you're seated you know
that you have a memory of it let the
Mind think while you're seated and even
if you lapse so to speak for as long as
that lapsing for as long as that
forgetfulness was not infected by lust
aversion doubt
hindrances uh your mindfulness has
remained uninterrupted in other words
your forgetfulness was something you
were mindful of the reference has
contained it rightly
and I think I said that in some early
videos from Sri Lanka like learn how to
forget mindfully in other words when
you're forgetting does not automatically
go into lust version delusion cuz you
kept an eye on those three
characteristics and avoid them
intentionally because you can't
accidentally start thinking about the
last lustful thoughts and perpetuate
them they might present themselves but
you will be taking them up and then
engaging with them further and that is
what interrupts so if you don't go in
that direction even if you spend 6 hours
of Just Thoughts thinking and pondering
doesn't matter if everything else your
situation remains unchanged and you
don't go in the domain of lust diversion
distraction hindrances your mindfulness
is is uh
unremitting and that's why it's
effortless as well because it's not you
putting it Forward constantly I'm
mindful mindful no the reference is the
body enduring
there so all you need to do is just
touch face with it every now and then so
to speak everything else is contained
with it like you know you have fenced
your property thoroughly there cannot
property thoroughly there cannot
be last aversion delusion finding way in
you have confidence in it now you let
the cows Grace and you stop seeing them
they go behind the tree go behind the
stack of hay go down the down the valley
it's still within the B within the
within the fence of it or like seated
position so
doesn't matter if you don't see them you
know that you will see them when they
come
up but for that to develop that
confidence that's that diligence in
regard to Greed diversion delusion
choices of greed diversion delusion not
I the image of last full image I must
get no no no you had it what did you do
when you had it well all scared CU you
were affected by want to get rid of it
that's over we're doing it oh really
welcoming it thinking about it giving it
a bit more I'll let it have a bit longer
then I'll deal with it no you shouldn't
have done that even for a millisecond
longer so work your way on that
level well yeah the fence will be
established and then you can let the
cows graze and thoughts think whatever
they want to think mind think whatever
it wants to
think CU that was never a problem